"The Best Diet for Fatty
Liver Disease Treatment"
Nonalcoholic fatty liver
disease is now the most frequent
chronic liver disease thanks,
in part, to our epidemic
of obesity, now even seen in children.
As many as nearly 70 to
80% of obese children
may have fatty liver disease.
Why do we care?
Because a fatty liver can
progress into fatty hepatitis,
which can cause scarring
and liver cirrhosis,
which is bad enough
without also causing you
to develop liver cancer, too.
Okay, so what’s the source of the
liver fat in fatty liver disease?
There are three main sources:
the excess sugar in our diet,
excess fat in our diet,
and the fat spilling over
from your own excess body fat.
How do we know excess
dietary sugar is bad?
Because it’s been put to the test.
If you randomize teens with
fatty liver disease to a diet
low in free sugars (meaning
added sugar and sugary beverages),
they experience a significant
improvement within eight weeks.
Given this new data, a liver
journal editorial read,
“[a] strong argument can
be made that we are beyond
any period of uncertainty
about the harmful effects
of excess sugar consumption
and that we must now act ...
to inform the public of the health
risks of eating too much sugar.”
How do we know excess
dietary fat is bad?
Because it’s been put to the test.
Randomize people to the
same low-calorie diet,
but one that’s low-fat
versus one that’s high-fat,
and within just two
weeks the low-fat diet
decreased liver fat by 20%,
whereas the same number
of calories on a high-fat
diet increased liver fat by 35%!
On the low-fat diet, insulin
levels went down about 15%,
and on the high-fat diet,
insulin levels went up about 15%.
Low-carb and ketogenic diet
advocates are always talking
about how you have to eat
more fat and less carbs
to keep your insulin levels down,
but the exact opposite
happens when it’s
actually put to the test.
Even a single high-fat meal
not only increases liver fat
but also insulin resistance.
Within four hours, your whole-
body insulin sensitivity
can drop by 25%; so, your
body has to pump out
that much more insulin.
As the accompanying editorial put it,
a single fat dose packs a punch.
So, to help prevent or
treat fatty liver disease,
patients should limit or
avoid eating fat-rich foods.
While more long-term clinical
trials are always needed,
based on current evidence,
we would recommend a diet
low in fat, notably
saturated fat, so low in meat,
dairy, and junk, and low in
reﬁned carbs, notably soda.
Saturated fat is not only
more metabolically harmful
for the human liver than
unsaturated fat, saturated fat
is more harmful than straight sugar.
If you overfeed people
with 1,000 calories
of saturated fat
(like cheese and coconut oil),
unsaturated fat (like nuts and olive oil),
or sugar (like soda and candy),
overeating 1,000 calories a day
of anything isn’t good for you,
but the saturated fat
increased liver fat 55%,
significantly more than
the unsaturated fats, with
the candy coming in in-between.
So, in terms of weight loss,
although beneﬁcial,
certain diets can actually
cause or exacerbate this disease,
such as very low-carbohydrate,
high-fat diets,
whereas those eating
healthy plant-based diets
may lower the risk of fatty liver disease.
For example, the consumption
of legumes (beans, split peas,
chickpeas, and lentils) is
associated with a lower risk
of fatty liver, up to 65%
lower odds eating more beans.
Now, in this study, they weren’t
looking at people eating
strictly plant-based diets,
just more or less so.
It’s harder to study those eating
completely meat-free diets
since they currently represent
just a small segment
of the U.S. population.
But what about Americans
of Indian descent?
Those originating from the
Indian subcontinent are one
of the fastest growing ethnic
groups in the United States,
and they appear to
largely retain their diets,
with about the same
percentage of vegetarians
as in India—nearly 40%.
We know in India itself,
nonvegetarians (those who eat meat)
are at significantly higher
risk of fatty liver disease.
In Taiwan, you see the same thing:
vegetarians at significantly lower risk.
And even the vegetarians
who were affected had
significantly less liver scarring.
Their data suggests that
replacing a single serving of soy
with a serving of meat or
fish was associated with
12% to 13% increased risk
of fatty liver disease.
But what about here
in the United States?
Eating vegetarian was
associated with being slimmer,
having better blood sugars,
better cholesterol,
and less than half the
odds of fatty liver disease.
You don’t know if it’s
cause-and-effect, though,
until you... put it to the test.
In an effort to reverse
a fatty liver patient’s
inflammatory bowel disease
with a plant-based diet,
liver inflammation was
dramatically improved.
But, he also lost about 9 pounds
in the first 11 days
thanks to eating healthy;
so, it’s hard to tease out
the specific diet effects.
In fact, you have to be
careful about rapid weight loss,
because all that extra fat
being broken down can flood
into the blood stream and
sometimes make things worse.
So, for fatty liver disease
patients, losing like
three pounds a week might be safer.
Even though plant-based diets
have yet to be properly
be put to the test in a
randomized clinical trial
for fatty liver disease, I
would submit that they are
still the best diet for fatty liver disease.
Not based on a single case report,
but based on the fact
that cardiovascular disease
is the most common cause
of death among patients
with fatty liver disease (not liver failure).
And we do have randomized
controlled trials
proving that a healthy plant-based
diet and lifestyle program
can reverse heart disease, opening
up arteries without drugs,
without surgery, without stents.
Yes, patients with fatty liver
disease and fatty hepatitis
may indeed eventually develop
cirrhosis of the liver,
but only if they don’t die of
cardiovascular diseases first.